Where was it? That happened. Okay, so this sell-off here, we moved from here to here almost within like three seconds. It was rapid, primarily a function of a headline coming out. The headline was to do with the UK and there's a certain budget that the UK negotiating team with the European Union for Brexit. So it happened in regards to that. It was basically negative news.
and price sold off.
It continues selling off all day.
And then I think around here,
the EU filed a lawsuit against the UK
for breaking some kind of fucking agreement.
And then I think here,
the UK committed
to actually solving some contentious issue
around Northern Ireland border
when we do leave Europe properly
or European Union properly.
And then this is more,
I don't know what happened here, to be honest.
I would assume that was also a headline,
some sort of event.
but most of the volatility we've seen today is off the back of some type of event
creating their conditions because what happens is
if I basically told you right now in the next 10 seconds
something significant in terms of information is going to come out news
which will influence price right
you don't know what's going to come out would you be taking a position right here right now
would you leave sell orders here would you leave buy orders here
No.
So typically around an event, you have to bear in mind, it's not human traders, right?
So the time, like the time element around responding to news, for us, it could be class as instantaneous.
What I'm saying is you have firms like certain HFT firms, high-frequency trading firms,
that pay for real time up-to-date data feeds.
So this is a data feed.
prices going up, data is being import into this platform
from some kind of server connected to
the data in the data centers that are connected
to the liquidity providers.
You can pay for
mad, mad, mad, fast data feeds
that cost about 100K a month with Bloomberg.
You pay $100,000 a month.
You get the HFT data feed,
which updates prices, I think millions of times a second.
There's nanoseconds, the price is updated.
Yeah.
Right?
When you have that data feed,
you could argue that they're seeing
the next price move slightly ahead of us
but like I said they're operating on a picosecond basis
so they can before that price move happens
so imagine imagine they see price update first
then it's reflected on my screen
and there's only let's say
I don't know 100 microseconds between them
yeah within that 100 microsecond period
they can't capitalize on it
because within that 100 microsecond period
which is 100 millionths of a second,
they could operate,
they could execute hundreds of times.
So the point I'm basically making here
is the speed advantage that these tech-based participants
have, fast money has, is impossible to be.
We cannot beat it.
And when new information comes out across the internet,
any news feed, any online news feed,
any like TV news feeds
these HFT firms are already connected
to those you get it so they're scouring the internet
at any given second looking for new information
when that new information hits
before me and you have had time to process
price moving up they've already scarred the internet
they've already made a decision to trade
they've already probably removed liquidity
to avoid taking the wrong side of the market
so a specific effect takes place
basically all of that what I said is leading up to this point
around events when we don't know what's going to happen next
or in response to a new piece of information,
the liquidity just evaporates.
Equity is limit orders.
Limit orders provide the counterparty,
you know,
the opposite side of a transaction.
For you to trade,
you need a limit order there to match with.
So if I said to you now,
right now this very minute,
somebody's buying one million.
It's quite reasonable to say
that one million of pound
is being brought right now.
For that to happen and price not move that much,
there has to be one million sell limit orders,
no?
Yeah.
now if there was a new piece of information that just came out and that one million disappeared
there was no one million sell limit order there and then a one million market order buy came
through what's going to happen to price yeah shoot up it shoots so even though that volume
wasn't that great you know that one million volume is happening anyway um the effect the volatility
popping off is more a function of liquidity drawing away to avoid the orders being selected or
them to take the wrong side of the market. So typically around events, those high-speed market
participants have the capacity to remove liquidity very, very quickly, and you see the book
lighten up massively. So where is it? I can tell you for free, this is 100%. You know,
you're going to observe this other time, yeah? So you're going to be watching prices, it'll be normal,
and then you look at your calendar, and say NFP or interest rate decision or monitor,
is a decision, whatever.
Then you'll see how price is behaving around then.
And then the minute it comes out, price will do something.
The way this forms is exactly like this is forming, basically.
You get it.
The ticking, the tick frequency, the pipa distance, the volatility,
that price takes on, the market takes on,
is uniquely, uniquely different to any other instance that you'll observe in the market.
So visually just, you know, I can.
visually tell you that there was a event here and you'll see it over time basically i'm just saying
bear with me you'll see it yeah so you would have had some type of information hit the market there
probably headline liquidity scour was out the market so limit orders are removed to avoid the orders
getting picked off and any volume that comes in just simply push his price chasing behind
wherever the liquidity is you get it that happened here uh it happened also yeah so
This is a much, much more aggressive version of liquidity disappearing.
You have a similar effect, but not that aggressive, going on here.
So when you push past certain thresholds, here are there sell liquidity, here this sell liquidity, here this sell liquidity.
There was sell liquidity that travel down with price.
And then once price pushes past a certain threshold, that sell liquidity can just disappear, right?
It could have been very, very, very thick here, and then suddenly it's very, very, very thin and sparsely spread out.
And typically, that's what's happening.
So whenever you have these types of shifts from a stable area of price
into something that I call mid-flow,
it's basically one-sided liquidity.
You have thick buyers here,
but a lack of sell liquidity in the way to match the buyers with.
So if I told you that this is buy liquidity and this is sell liquidity,
which direction requires more market orders to push price there?
Sell.
Yeah.
So you need much.
much more selling than the required buying to push price up.
Yeah.
Right.
And that's typically what's going on in these periods.
So you push price past a certain threshold.
A change occurs in the state of liquidity.
You had thick liquidity here, now suddenly quite thin.
As a function of adverse selection limiting, I guess, measures,
liquidity providers, market makers, those two are interchangeable.
Those terms are.
They basically, they don't want to be taken on huge short positions here when
the likelihood of price
moving against them
is quite high
so imagine
a liquidity provider
received a hundred million
order to buy pound
that hundred million
is going to get split
into small pieces
because if I'm buying
a hundred million here
or a client
is buying a hundred million here
the likelihood of him
finding a hundred million
seller there is quite
it's almost minimal
it's never going to happen
that was I talking about
so 100 million
it's unlikely
that that order is going to get filled
there
so that order has to get split up.
In other words,
if the liquidity provider receives a big order
and they know it's going to push price up,
they're not going to basically be willing to provide liquidity in that direction.
So they want to avoid taking on short positions.
They remove some liquidity,
the lighten it up and it kind of results in this dynamic.
Exactly.
In response.
Last session was in that session.
Yeah.
And then this is that happening.
By the way, the liquidity provider removal and liquidity is all automated.
It's happening.
They are themselves.
they have the capacity to operate on these nanoseconds, sub-second time basis,
yeah, on the timeframes.
The same thing's going on here, but just on a much more,
there's a greater imbalance being created.
There's much less liquidity here than there is obviously here.
You can see similar effect.
And then the rest of the time, where there is no kind of significant event,
prices much more stable, right?
Anyway, we're going to get into all this stuff.
and look for another
yeah
you won't find it yeah
is there any significance
behind that gap
that was made there
yeah it's just a pricing feed
like this feed
would be a bit different
to the gap on yeah
it's no nothing
okay
there's really matter
what's gonna say
oh yeah
tomorrow is Friday
I think it's NFP
so around half half one
yeah at 13 30 hours
or it might be 12th day
I don't know
NFP will come out
if you look at the price
the way it takes around
that time you'll see that it has a similar kind of effect anyway last session we went through
what so we obviously discussed how dealer behavior and market participant behavior can create these
kind of inefficiencies and the market can run further than it showed or the market ends up
running further than it should because of this type of dynamic where they remove liquidity
what else did we touch on um that was heavily the same you were shown
me like examples and stuff of it on live charts um so i introduced you to this idea of a vacuum
being left behind yeah yeah we've discussed market structure a bit we've discussed that
prize goes at less liquid side we then started to discuss how less liquidity can be you know
how there can be an environment of less liquidity because of the behaviors of liquidity providers
that's what we discussed last week of a session but then also i expanded
followed on from that
and said the effect
of liquidity providers
removing liquidity is
price obviously travels further
that's one effect
yeah
then as a result of price traveling further
and as a result of liquidity
being removed
there's less transactions that happen
as that move is happening
to the downside you get it
yeah yeah that made sense
there's less liquidity
for the cell volume to match with
on the way down so this is what you would call
a low volume traded area
even though they could be heavy heavy selling
there was no actual transactions
that were massive in amounts
because the transaction is a volume
plus liquidity or matching with the liquidity
you get it
yeah yeah that makes sense
so it leaves behind a thinly traded low volume area
which you could class as a vacuum
so no real sell liquidity or by liquidity
builds up there leaving behind that kind of vacuum
so that was point number two
and then the third point is
by the time the cell volume dries off
it's left behind such a thinly traded area of prices
where there's little little liquidity
you again have a weaker side of sell liquidity
and it doesn't even require that much of the thick side
and buy liquidity to stop price set dropping off
and it's quite easy to push price back into range
it requires much less volume to push price back into range
by that point
so basically what I'm saying is at these points down here
you have a skewed book.
Yeah.
Right?
You could say that at that exact point right there, hypothetically,
you had, for example, 10 million bi-liquity at this area here,
you only had 1 million cell liquidity,
and you had 1 million, 1 million, 1 million, 1 million, 1 million,
much more thinly spread out.
Sorry, what I'm saying?
Makes sense.
Yeah, it's much more spread out, and it's only 1, 2, 3, 3,
for 5 million spread out over
ex-fanny prices
compared to 10 million in a single
pot here.
It requires much less buying
the push price up
and that's typically what's happening
at these points of exhaustion.
So we've reached a conclusion
that you need to validate over time
because anything I say
is just basically you can do your research
you can validate it
but you need to experience it
and build your own experience
of seeing it happens
so you believe in it.
you'll believe what you observe much more than you believe what I'm telling you.
Do you get it?
So like I said, you're at the start.
You need to kind of question anything I'm telling you and take a, take it with a pinch of salt.
Try to invalidate what I'm saying.
And I'm telling, basically, I make the bet we that you won't be able to do it.
Either way, yeah, we reached a conclusion that trading under a condition where there's a skewed book.
If you can identify it, it results in very, very high probability of trade working in your favor or price going in your favor.
you get it we need edge if we trade under this condition probably is skewed in our favor
so that can consistently bring us if we're trading under that condition it can consistently give
us price moves predictability of future price moves and that's exactly what we're trying to do when
we're using price charts if you're a candlestick trader and you're looking at price action
you're making the assumption that candlesticks are completely sufficient in predicting
future moves and when we trade under a skewed buck it's on
you know, the rules of trading force price to go to less liquid side and it gives us edge.
So yeah, we reached that conclusion.
It's very important because we've now answered or is a possible answer to this problem
of when you're trying to build a trade plan, when do I trade, you know, when do I engage the market?
When am I trading?
What am I looking for?
Yeah.
It looks like inefficient price action.
That's one way of trading, yeah.
but when it comes to like these inefficiencies
it's critical to understand why price goes up
not just yeah people will call it just an inefficiency
also what they will say is that only this part of the price run
was inefficient yeah but it's all of it right
technically the whole fucking price move to the downside was inefficient
right because throughout it
not huge amounts of buy liquidity was provided
so sellers couldn't match with them in a massive amount
or rather the sell transactions
were split up and stretched that out like a chewing-go.
The effect of that is, like we discussed, a less liquid sign.
So, that being said,
trading under a condition of a skewed book
is a solution to this problem of not having edge.
Also, what do we discuss?
We continued discussing EBS.
What happened with prime brokerage?
What was the effect of prime brokerage on EBS?
Did we say anything to do with EBS?
last time.
Yeah.
I think the
So what is EBS?
So EBS is the electronic
brokerage system.
For who?
Oh, is...
Post-equity on there.
And the banks and stuff.
Okay, so...
There's like tier one banks
and then tier two banks.
Yeah.
What is EBS for?
What was the salute...
Why did...
Why was EBS revolutionary
to trading?
of FX in 99s.
Because you can see live
prices on there.
But the banks were connected to each other
and they would tell each other live prices anyway.
Or at least you could ring the bank
and they would tell you the live price anyway.
So that, no, basically.
Basically, we had a problem
before EBS.
When a bank tried to clear a trade with another bank,
they had to make sure
there was a credit relationship there
and I had to be done manually
in person by people
so there wasn't an automated check-in
for credit relationships
so when a bank
wants to trade 100 million
short GVP USD
with Bank 2
that trade the 100 million isn't passed over
immediately, you're settled in two days
you get it
Yeah
Oh was this the part where you said that
There's a lady
And she's just sitting there
And she's slow and stuff
Yeah
if somebody is having to manually check each transaction
between a bank
or large transaction between a bank
to make sure that they have the necessary credit relationships
a transaction can't be finalised until that's happened
you get it so imagine you're trying to buy GDP right now
on your platform on mt4 or on iC market share
you click the button and then it says okay we're going to check
that you have enough margin in your account
let a man let a guy do it on his computer let and pull
name off, type Zanin, check that you have it, and then click okay, that is, you know,
your transaction is good enough. What if in that time, price moved away?
You know, in two days it would?
No, no, but the transaction settled in two days. That's different to opening the transaction.
Oh, okay.
In other words, I can open up a trade right now on GDPUSD and then close it, but not get paid for
that profit or lost, basically, until two days time. Okay.
You get it.
but if I'm trying to open up a transaction
for cable at 1, 2894
and they have to check
that I have the necessary margin
the credit relationships with the counterparty
by the time they do that
price might already be up five pips
I can't trade the price I want to
so you know
the market this type of
this type of approach
in creating transactions manually
or at least check in credit
between banks manually
was inefficient
the market wasn't doing a good job
when facilitating trade
so EBS came out as a solution to that
it did pre-trade credit checks
before the trade happened
if you were on EBS as a bank
and you could see Bank 2's liquidity
you had to already have the relationship with them
you get it
EBS checked this electronically
before the trade happened
so if now Bank 1 wanted to buy
or sell 100 million GDP to Bank 2
the fact that they can sell to them on EBS
means they have a credit relationship already
and it'd get filled instantaneously.
Yeah.
You get it.
So that was the benefit of EBS.
It increased the efficiency of matching transaction number one.
Number two, it made it a bit more transparent.
It made the price formation more transparent
because EBS ran like a single order book,
like an exchange.
What does that mean?
What, the single order book?
Yeah.
All the banks can see the live prices and price being formed on EBS.
Yeah, but what happens on a single order book?
You can see the volume on each side, the liquidity on each side.
Yes.
All of it's in one location.
Do you get it?
Rather than somebody trading on this order book,
then somebody trading on this order book,
and then somebody trading on this order book,
the volume could be 30% or 33.3.33, 33, 33, 33.
you get it
the majority of the volume
was on a single order book
for your USD at least
in a single venue
where all the banks were connected together
so they're all sitting at the same table
and a single order book
a single order book means a single price
if I run my own order book
and then you run your own order book
and then your broker runs their own order book
you could potentially have three different prices
if there's a single order book
and the prices are forming on there
all the transactions are happening on
there, there is only one price.
So again, made the market more efficient
in price distribution because
it allowed for dealers to connect to the
same price created on this
trustworthy advanced platform for that time.
So what eventually
happened there is banks all
migrated to hedging their risk
on EBS.
Rather than connected to each other directly,
rather than ringing my man up
at Bank 3, I'm like, yeah, you know, we want to trade
this, get that fat dishes check here, all that
off. They could just do it all on EBS straight away.
There was a migration over to EBS.
And this is where, of course, the bulk of the volume,
I think 70% of daily trading volume all the way to like 2008 was happening on EBS for
EuroUSD, which is the most traded, most liquid asset, currency pair, sorry, in FX.
Okay.
Right? So there's major, major changes happening.
one of the major changes here is single price
and the price formation all happens on EBS
so if you had
when they had
bank one
bank two bank three bank four they're all connected
to the central platform
each of these banks will have their client so here's
Amazon a 996 here's some shit company there
here's another company here's another company
all right we'll call it A B CD
A B A you know goes long an XM
the bank hedges there on EBS price moves on EBS so it changes there first these guys know about the
change first before the rest of these guys do and them okay you get it so these guys at the
informational edge on on the price formation it was all happening on the same venue that they could
see so once the price changed here they then reflected it back out to the market so simply
being on EBS you get to saw fractions of a second before the rest of the market where
price was going. Also, if all the liquidity is on a single book, when company A is ringing
to buy 100 million, they're asking the bank to give them a quote, right? They're asking the
bank, so it was voice broken back then. Apple rings Bank One. We want 100 million GDP USD. What's
the quote? They wouldn't say buy or sell. They just say, I want 100 million bid ask. The bank would
quote them a bit and ask, but the bank could see the available buy liquidity and sell liquidity
for GDP USD at that time. And kind of, if they wanted to, they could add a spread on. But in
either case, they again could see what the current state of liquidity was for GDPUSD at that time.
For example, now if I said to you this, if all of these three other banks were heavily, heavily
selling GDPUSD at that time, because their clients were selling.
it. Right? So clients, all of these guys were selling GDPUSD telling the bank to fill it. The bank
would then have to go on EBS to hedge it. So you saw massive, massive, massive sell limit orders sitting
on the book. And then Apple sees that, sorry, Bank One sees that. Apple has just decided to buy
GbP USD. What could this bank potentially do? So heavy, heavy sell liquidity, which likely is
weak by liquidity, right?
Price on cable is being,
cable is being sold at that time.
Oh, yeah.
So it can hedge the position
and take the,
the cell on it because it's heavily being,
um,
they wouldn't even need to hedge that position,
yeah?
Because hedge means that they wouldn't take
the opposite side.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, so,
so when Apple buys,
they're obviously selling,
so they'll sell,
yeah, they'll just keep selling it.
They could take on a short position
against Apple.
so now the bank is short
prices already being sold on
GDP USD
the prices already
going down because GDPUSD is being
sold and again they could capture
some profit of that
so trading on EBS gave banks
of course
that information on edge
over everybody else but again
we have discussed how loads of information
leaked as well now
because the bank
let's just say in this instance
the bank was up to their risk
limit right
so they couldn't take on any more
positions without hedging them. And then Apple came with a hundred million buy order. The bank will
have to hedge it on EBS. The bank will have to hedge on EBS. So if Apple wants to buy, the bank has to
buy here and then sell back to Apple. So the bank has a buy position and a sell position. They
hedged. No problem. But the point making is information about 100 million being brought is now going
on to EBS. Everybody can see it. These guys might respond, creating more expensive.
enterprises for Apple. So it's a problem, it's a real issue. Their clients, FX is more client-based, sorry, it's
relationship-based. You know, the bank makes money by consistently quoting a bid and ask to their
clients. If they're getting shit fills or more expensive, you know, if their transaction or the
execution costs are too high for their clients, it may, you know, they're risking their clients
leaving them.
Right?
So if every time
Apple comes in and when they buy
a large amount, they're trying to buy it,
it results in slippage and price going
against them. Apple might
be dissatisfied by that
effect, yeah?
No? Yeah.
That's a really function of the reason
price slippage is occurring is because
all that information about Apple's trade
is reaching the central place where everybody can
see it and then they can respond to it as well.
Imagine a time
which is basically today,
where if Apple wanted to buy $100 million
nobody else would know about it
if Apple tasked their bank
so Apple buys $100 million
obviously the bank sells them $100 million
now the bank has $100 million short position
if nobody else knows
that the bank has a $100 million short position
it might make it easier for the bank to get out of that position
without price moving too aggressively
Yeah that's true
If suddenly you caught wind and everybody caught wind
that this bank is now short $100 million
they need to get out of that position, and Apple have just bought $100 million.
If that information becomes public knowledge,
price might move adversely, negatively affecting this bank,
making them in the future not want to provide liquidity to Apple,
and then Apple has to go and access liquidity of a central exchange,
obviously through the bank,
and that again will cause negative price volatility.
It will cause negative or higher transaction costs.
So when you're in this market of FX,
It is a conduit market where clients are not necessarily trying to make money.
A good majority of the transactions that happen on a daily basis are non-specletive.
They're not like me and you buying and selling currency to capture fucking 10-pips of it.
Right? It's more for operational reasons.
So, in order for banks to satisfy their client's needs,
they have to limit transaction costs for them.
And know what to do that, they have to be able to hide information sufficiently.
So the clients are being impacted by negative execution costs.
Yeah.
Do you get it?
It's all bank or sellers of liquidity, sell side and their relationships to the by side, namely the byside clients.
If Apple has a relationship with Deutsche Bank, for example, they might prefer to source liquidity of them for a number of reasons, costs.
execution costs basically, and also the marginalization of Doja Bank, Apple might find it safe
to have them as a counterparty for large transactions. Because, to be honest, a multinational
cooperation, when they're filtering off hundreds of billions of risk in currency risk per year,
they wouldn't really want a counterparty like IC Markets. I see markets is a very risky business
that takes risk against their customers
at any given time
the market could blow up against them.
So, for example,
if Apple went long with IC markets
for 100 million,
GbP, USD,
and then IC markets went bust,
Apple is not going to get paid out.
There's real counterparty risk.
The same way, if I buy a car a few,
and a car turns out to be shit,
it's my risk.
It's a private transaction
between two parties,
it's bilateral risk.
Do you get it?
So that can be one of the reasons why, or that is one of the reasons, you have Tier 1 banks that are classed as Tier 1 capital, the safest capital in the world.
That's why large corporations, at least large corporations, they transact with banks at least, the buy liquidity of them.
There's lower counterparty risk, they're unlikely to go robust.
And secondly, they can provide relatively cheap transaction costs.
so that's that
what is prime brokerage
Prime brokerage is
it allowed
bank clients to access
other liquidity providers from
no no to access liquidity from other banks
perfect yeah over liquidity providers
banks tier 1 banks are the primary
liquidity providers in FX
so you had EBS
that was the primary exchange for price discovery
for your USD
all the banks
connected to it. And then suddenly
a prime brokerage client
of let's say Deutsche Bank can now access
liquidity from all the other banks
and it can directly post
liquidity on EBS.
What's the effect of that?
So someone's
brought it and then they're
posting it onto EBS?
No.
Before prime brokerage
the client would have to trade
directly with the bank and that's it.
Yeah. The bank
would quote them a bid and ask
for whatever volume the client wanted
now because of prime brokerage
the client of the bank can access liquidity
from any other interbank
equity provider
oh there might be better prices on the other ones
that's fine the bank would receive a commission
right if the bank is taken out of prime brokerage client
their client has posted up huge amounts of margin
the bank's vetted their business initially anyway
and simultaneously they charge them a commission per million traded.
It might be like $3,
but they'll charge them a commission per million
that the client trades in the interbank market.
It's like you come into me asking me to buy something.
I haven't got it, but my friend has it.
So I charge you a fee to passing you over to my friend,
I find this fee.
That's basically what prime brokerage is.
But of course, you don't go to see my friend,
you go through me.
I manage the transaction for you.
Now, that's effectively what bank
are doing with liquidity on prime brokerage.
But what I'm saying is
the prime brokerage client was given access
to EBS. They were
able to post orders
through the bank, obviously, directly
on EBS. So let's just say the prime brokerage
client is a small hedge fund. They're
sitting at the shitty law office. There's
a computer screen there.
When they place a buy limit order,
they're able to place it directly on
EBS. When they're seeing their prices,
the bid and the ask is coming
directly from EBS.
you get it and what happened with eBS like what was one of the main effects of eBS it provides a
informational advantage to ever sees it prices are formed here first and then everybody else sees
it are you following yeah so what's the significance of what i'm saying i know what you're saying
i don't understand the significance of what you said then you don't know what i'm saying if i could
if you knew where this price is going to go before everybody else does what's the significance of that
so if I can see what price is doing before everyone else
yeah you know you know what side the
the thing in the which side the orders are on
you have an informational advantage of the rest of the market
yeah so let's go back to this this why I'm going to keep repeating this point
until you make you know you have to you have to get it
EBS was it into dealer platform and is it into dealer platform
where the banks post liquidity on when the client
tasks the bank to fill
a order for them, the bank goes and
hedges, they used to go and hedge it on EBS.
Effectively,
what happened then is
the client's order
or the bank's order
would cause prices to change on EBS.
Can you see
what's happening on EBS?
No. No.
So you can't see the price changing
happening on EBS, but the banks can.
Okay. That means the bank's
know more about where price is going to go
or before you at least
than the rest of the market
that's an informational asymmetry
information is not being distributed
equally in this market
the banks knew about price and where it's going to go
when obviously EBS was the main
liquidity centre before the rest of the market
now what I'm saying is
suddenly because of prime brokerage
clients
can now access
the price formation of EBS
they can see happening
alongside the banks
so they can
they can also start posting liquidity
on EBS
now imagine if this
primary approach client was more technologically
advanced than some of these banks
they could post liquidity
take liquidity
they could
they had their speed advantage
the HFTs have
now what they can do is
basically, because they were more technologically savvy,
they were able to post tighter bids and offers on EBS.
Yeah.
They were able to, let's say a bank three.
Bank three is responding to buying coming in from Bank One, Bank Two and Bank Four.
And the Bank Three has a sell order.
What does Bank Three need to do?
If everybody else is buying and Bank three had a sell limit order,
what does this guy need to do?
I need to get rid of it.
if before he can get rid of it, imagine you could take it.
Imagine the prime brokerage client could quickly get to it before this number three could take it.
Imagine if the prime brokerage client could analyze the volume and the ticking and the changes in the liquidity available on EBS.
And they could make a decision about where the price is going to go next well before these banks.
They could exploit their lack of speed.
They could exploit their slowness.
They could even trick them.
right so what effectively started to happen here is these predatory type third party clients they were able to post liquidity on eBS they had now had an equal they had equal access to informational advantages that banks previously had and they were able to basically to keep it quite simple they're able to limit their exposure quite quickly so if prime brokerage client had a sell limit order on eBS
price started to shoot up
they could actually remove this
sell limit order by your head of everybody else
because of this people
yeah okay
right
as a function of this
these prime brokerage clients
they were typically hedge funds
hedge funds that invested heavily
into their own tech side
and simultaneously
they also started to provide liquidity
to smaller clients
because imagine
imagine being it this way
whenever this client takes on a position,
let's say short or long,
before these guys can respond to new information,
this firm can analyze incoming information
or they can look at the price ticking,
they can look at their volume
and assess which way price is going to go
well before everybody else.
They have a much greater capacity to manage risk.
So put it this way,
they go long on the bid.
So somebody hits their bid,
they had a buy limit order,
somebody sold into the bi-limber order.
If now new information comes or new volume comes
and it implies or is indicative of this asset
now likely selling off,
these guys can respond to that information
well before these guys. So they had a greater capacity
to manage their risk, especially when market making happens.
Because as a market maker, you're buying at the most expensive price,
you're selling at the cheapest price.
You need to be able to manage risk quite quickly, quite fast, basically.
these guys had a great capacity to do that.
So what eventually happened is
they started to take market share away from banks
in terms of providing liquidity.
They were able to,
so if these guys were quoting one-pip spread on GDP-USD
because of these guys' behaviours,
they could quote a 0.5 pips spread.
Okay.
If these guys are quoting 0.6 pips,
they could quote 0.4 pips.
Yeah, so clients would want to go to them more?
Yeah.
Clans would want to go to them.
but obviously you have to remember
a HFT firm has taken on much more proprietary risk
than a bank who's more regulated with their capital
so when you do have a large corporation like Apple
they don't necessarily care as much about the prices
than they do about the safety of transacting
with a safer firm versus a more risky firm
so some clients maintain the relationships with banks
other clients like smaller retail firms
retail brokers
small hedge funds
that couldn't really access
direct relationship with the banks
because they couldn't afford it
you would have
leveraged funds basically as well
they might
so small hedge funds basically
they might find it
they're willing
to accept the higher
counterparty risk for cheaper prices
so HFTs were taking
some market share
in providing liquidity
to the smaller side of the FX
whilst the large transactions
the corporate side of FX or the real money
so the pension fund fund trades
the types of trades which are massive in nature
and bring a high level of counterparty risk
they maintain the relationships with banks
so that's solved one issue
now we've reached a conclusion that
let's summarize
information leaks too much from client order flow
and there's there's participants on EBS now
that can exploit that information
and basically
making more costly for the end client
they can make it more costly for the end client.
So banks had that one problem, predatory aggressive type participants making them more costly for clients.
Number two, the same predatory aggressive type participants were able to exploit the slowness, the old infrastructure of banks at that time.
Yeah. Get it.
And obviously the third problem, the take your market share away from them.
Banks are raising money and making money.
The revenue stream is transactional base, providing liquidity.
the spread. And when somebody takes that client away from them, they lose a market share. So there
was these three major problems in and around 1998 onwards in FX. So that's why even last year,
sorry, in 2018, the largest liquidity providing firm in the world was a non-bank. It was a non-bank
called XTX markets. They were a technology firm with like 70 employees. They were the largest
liquidity provider market share-wise
in the whole fucking world.
And obviously, J.P. Morgan was second,
etc. Then 2019, J.P. Morgan
took back the top spot. So it's been a constant fight
ever since then between non-bank tech firms
who provide cheap liquidity
versus a conventional bank market makers.
That's the basic history behind it.
But now we're going to discuss what the banks did
to fight back against these three problems.
and how that affected the market as we know it today.
So imagine when a bank receives an order from Apple of $100 million,
they didn't have to go to EBS to find liquidity for it.
If they could internalize that order, i.e. keep it in-house, match it off with other clients in-house,
less information leaks out to the market.
Nobody else knows that that transaction happened between the two parties.
Right.
And simultaneously, those predatory-type participants,
who are exploiting the inefficiencies of banks on EBS
now don't have access to the information.
You get it?
Now the bank doesn't have to go to EBS to post liquidity on there.
They can just manage it all in-house.
So they're matching the client's orders against each other?
They can do it in-house, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
That's what you call internalization.
Now, also think about it this way.
If the bank wants to connect to EBS, that's a different party.
EBS is given,
the right to manage the
execution of orders and match traders and buyers together
for that price
is going to bounce here.
Imagine you brought it there
and there's your stop loss.
Price is already going up.
You have a
two-pip stop. That's one R
that's nearly two
that's two R. These
are the type of trades that I would normally take.
To be honest, I would have taken this if I wasn't
on a call.
That would be...
You're nuts, you are.
That's like literally a live, a live call that you just said,
oh, it's going to go up and it just shut up.
That'd be four R.
Yeah, that's mad.
Even though it's only eight pips, you would have captured four R for it.
Something popped up on the bottom right hand of your screen?
Yeah, yeah, no, no.
Okay. I don't know what he said. He just popped up.
It was a, basically this fucking guy, bro.
His name's Flipper Boy George from London.
he is a fraud boy
that motherfucker makes millions of trading Dow Jones
so what I'm doing is I'm practicing demo
on as you can see this is a demo account
I'm practicing demo on Dow Jones
I might shift over from GDPUSD to Dow Jones
because I only trade GDPUSD
I know I have other assets open
I look at these like once a fucking month
I primarily trade GDPUSD
I may in the future
switch over to this
okay yeah so you're just testing
it out basically. Yeah, I'm just testing
out. Anyway, back to what we
were talking about.
Yeah, so if the bank can internalize the trade
and match the clients off in-house,
the information doesn't reach EBS.
Also, it's cheaper for them because they don't have to pay
commissions to EBS
to make, you know, basically to fill the orders
for them.
So it's kind of a win-win situation.
So in order for, in order to fight back
against third parties or non-banks
accessing EBS,
banks themselves,
invested heavily, heavily in their internal infrastructures,
in the pricing engines, how they match trades together
in order to keep information in-house.
In order to match information in house.
That's why if you look at FX flaws today,
they're dominated by, not by traders,
you know, not those fast traders who eat bacon cobs in the morning,
they're more going to be quantitative traders,
basically just muskies.
that's what FX looks like today
that's how it's progressed
these banks invest heavily
in developing their own technologies
to internalize trades
increase the capacity to internalize trades
basically
operate on a similar level
to these third-party firms
you know
you know the ones that
like smack themselves and stuff
yeah I know I know
some of the stuff
they subscribe to is like just so
fucking crazy bro like
yeah like it's not
not with the teachings at all
nuts
like anyway
um
so yeah
basically one saying it was a bank
back they tried to take mortgagee back by
stopping um posting liquidity on eBS
let's just give you an example today
where previously eBS account for 70% of the volume
or where volume transacted on these 70% of the volume
transacted on eBS now it's less than 20%
a day. It's less than 20% a day now. Now, today, it's less than 20% of the daily volume of your
USD. Yeah. It doesn't transact from EBS anymore. Rather, the banks just internalize it.
They develop their capacity to internally fill the trades, match them off against clients,
or take the opposite side against them. Yeah. Um, so yeah, that's a cool fact. Um, but anyway,
actually looking at what goes on here. So if he, he was a client, so Zayne,
you go along like I said
you're a private brokerage client at this instance
you can go along against any of a bank that you want to
this bank has essentially
three options to fill your trade
they can go take the short against you
they can
if you long it
there might be a client
me that has a sell limit order
and if yours is a market order long
they could if that's where the liquidity is
hold your volume up there to fill it with
match it off against fine
simultaneously they could take the opposite side of your trade on the offer so you and market order long on the ask price on the offer and they could just simply wait for somebody to hit their bid as well so they capture the spread okay right so that is three options they have all a class that has in keeping the volume in house internalizing right so they internalize that order that you your order but
Obviously, the last option is to, if you went long,
they can simultaneously go longer any other bank and then go short against you.
So much, much their risk.
Hedge your risk out externally.
That's called externalizing your trade.
Obviously, we've discussed the effects of it's externalizing information leaks.
All these other guys can respond.
It can result in more expensive prices for you.
It can make a relatively more difficult for the bank to hedge their risk without price
moving adversely against them.
if that happens
there's something
called a prisoner's dilemma
if every time you trade
the bank has to trade
externally in the market
and every time
they trade externally in the market
it results in
these guys
price moving against them
and then losing out
on that trade
yeah
right
they then just going to turn around
to you
classify you as aggressive
or toxic
and quote you
wider spreads
so where previously
with this bank
you would get
for example
0.6 pip spread
suddenly now because they're having to externalize your trade to fill it
and that's become costly for them
they're just going to turn around to you and like fuck you mate
we're not going to quote you for example 1.5 pips spread
because if they if they now quote you 1.5 pips spread
it's easier for them to manage their risk basically
all right so this is what you call profiling the customers
they do that the same way a retail broker
when you trade with the retail broker or anybody trades
with retail broker, initially
you're classified as BBBOR or
unprofitable. 70% of traders, retail traders
lose money. The broker
doesn't even have to check who you are.
As long as you're trading
a relatively small account,
as long as you're over-leveraged
systematically, they'll just trade against you.
So when you go along, they go short against you. They don't hedge
your risk. So this is B-BBEC?
That's B-Bok.
because 70% of retail trades lose
if they just went short against the majority of retail
over time they're guaranteed to win money
I'll take it with an A-book then as well
yeah there's an A-buck where
if the brokers reached their risk limit
so they can't take any more exposure
or if the client is good
so the client is trading too large
if the client has too much money in his account
and they can
classify them as, let's say,
toxic, they'll then
have to hedge his trades out in the market.
Okay.
All right. But that's
that. And the bank's essentially doing
the same thing. If you have a corporate client
like Apple, they
don't necessarily try to make
money off FX. They probably
would even like sometimes take trades against
the underlying direction
of the market. So
it's a high likelihood when it's corporate
clients, the bank is trying to take the opposite side against that.
If cable's on offer, so cable being sold, and I go along with the bank as one of their clients,
it's very likely the bank can just take the opposite side against me, go short,
whoever's selling cable is trying to find buyers, yeah?
This bank should have passed me to do with the buyers, but he doesn't.
He keeps the volume for himself.
He internalizes the trade.
that essentially results in
less available by liquidity
so price continues to drop
and simultaneously the bank profits from it
so we already know all these things
so one final thing
I'll say to be a prime brokerage client
in 2015 before that was quite easy
the banks were taking a lot of risk given
prime brokerage clients basically credit
to loads of firms
small retail brokers
small hedge funds etc etc
in 2015 the USD Swiss franc
crashed right
The bank, one of these tier one banks had given credit to a brokerage firm called FXCM that we discussed last time.
FXCM was taking risk against these clients.
So when its clients were going long, the FXCM was going short against them.
Their clients were short, U.S.D. Swiss francs, some of them.
So FXCM was long against some of those clients.
U.S. Swiss franc crashed like 1,000, 2,000 pips within 10 and 15 minutes.
Why did that happen?
There was, basically, there's something called a flaw.
The Swiss National Bank, the Swedish Central Bank,
they were systematically devaluing their currency.
They were making it cheap.
And then suddenly they came out with news that they're going to stop doing that.
They're going to let it appreciate.
And that very day, USD Swiss franc crashed.
So USD crashed against Swiss franc.
was frank went crazy.
They were basically a flash crash
and FXCM was long
during that flash crash against his client.
So didn't FXM know
anything about it beforehand?
FXM isn't a dealer.
Okay, that's just the prime brokerage client?
They're just a client similar to me and you.
Okay, okay, okay.
They have more information about the market
than me and you,
but they are not price makers
they don't influence prices
if FXCM was a direct client
of DOSHA Bank, DOSHA Bank would almost
always take the risk against them
because any flow that arises from
FXEM could be classified as benign
they're never going to have informed
well-informed traders
that take certain views of the market
that I like to push in that direction
simultaneously FXCM is not going to trade
enough volume to ever push
the market significantly in any direction
so they're never going to be classed
That's uninformed.
Okay.
Always.
So uninformed, a benign volume is the most favorite, basically, for banks.
Because not only they capture the spread, they can take the risk against them.
Yeah.
So, yeah, FXEM, they ended up, because they're a risk-taking broker, they go short when you go long.
It's a terrible model, you know, it's a risk model, but FXEM was probably banking millions before this happened.
they ended up with a minus 200 million hold that day.
So they didn't have enough cash to pay out their clients.
They didn't have enough cash anymore to maintain their margin
that's required for their prime brokerage, right?
And in other words, these banks were very unlikely
to receive the money that they need to make up for the losses.
All right?
So ever since 2015, these banks just caught all the relationships.
Some banks now don't even offer prime brokerage.
If you have a prime brokerage relationship with a bank, you apply two weeks ahead.
They look, you apply with your whole financial statement and the financial basic audit of your firm.
They go through it with a fine tooth cone.
You need a balance sheet of minimum 200 million.
You need incoming volume or revenue of a minimum, probably in a tens of billions per year.
And only then they will think about accepting you.
When you apply for a prime brokerage client now, you don't choose for the banks.
You don't choose the bank.
The bank chooses you because they're giving you credit.
It's like a mortgage, right?
In other words, what I'm saying is only today in 2020, you only really access prime brokerage if you're a large hedge fund, if you're a pension fund, if you're a very significant firm that the bank cares about.
So did they start doing this after 2015 when FXCM did that?
They became, yeah, they became much more selective after 2050.
The point I'm making to you is that these banks who are effectively setting the prices that we all copy,
that your broker copies and posts on your platform, these guys are only dealing with the largest firms.
They do not care about small transactions.
We account for as retail effects, I think, I think, up to $2 billion per volume a day.
Well, it might be 20 billion.
Let's just say a 20 billion volume per day.
Well, yeah, there's no way in the trillion, so yeah, that's definitely small.
The Spotfx market is $2 trillion a day.
This is chump change.
Although it's 20 billion that the bank would like to take on,
most of this volume never reaches the banks anyway,
because the broker, your retail broker decides to go short against the majority of it.
It's similar to, it's similar to bank.
internalizing trades rather than posting on EBS. If you're here, Zane, and here's your retail
broker, when you go long and they go short, this is the only trade that happened. Nobody else
knows in the whole fucking dunya that this trade happened other than you are the retail brokerage.
It's a private transaction. If obviously the bank externalized the trade and then pass
it over to the liquidity providers, then you are trading directly on the market. But the
majority of
effects,
their flow
stays internal
to retail brokers.
The retail broker
model is really
profitable because
they trade against
their clients.
Hence,
this notion that
banks are trading
against you
and they're
taunting your
stop losses.
How can they
hunt a stop loss
that never came
to them?
Yeah.
How could they
hunt a order?
It's like me
saying that,
I don't know,
it's ridiculous.
It's like me going,
it's like you
paying for something
on eBay and then
like me
affecting that.
transaction i can't access your fucking eBay account we're in completely two different worlds
that makes a lot of sense now because you know i used to i used to be one of them people who was
like oh yeah yeah they they hunt stuff losses and then when she came to actually tell me that
they they don't and you explained why then yeah that changed your volume i highly highly
doubt if you're a majority of your volume has reached the market ever
tell me the broker's you've been trying it with yeah i see my
markets.
Yeah, your volume never reaches a market ever.
I see markets is your sole counterpoint.
And they're the only person you're trading against.
So it's completely bullshit.
To be it's not.
It's really not because I, in reality, you're getting 0.1 pips spreads, very, very tight spreads.
Plus a commission that's worth 0.8 pips, right?
They're filling your trade almost instantaneously because they want to keep
you want as a client in order for you to keep giving them money if you're a benign or uninformed
trader you'll get amazing execution we won't try to bump you they're not trying to do you over
and trick you they will want you they want you to keep coming back you're not costly for them
they can capture the spread against you and trade against you they want you to come back as many times
possible so it makes sense when a retail broker takes the opposite side against benign flow
but the problem arises
when you're a profitable trader
trying to trade with a B-Bock broker
then they're going to start giving you problems
then you're going to get higher latency
they're not going to fill your orders as quick
as possible because they happen to hedge
out in the market I reckon
they might even do questionable
stuff like
purposely taking a long time
to hedge your trade out in the market
avoiding
increase in the latency so it gives them extra time
to try and make money
on your information from your orders
but yeah
have you had any problems with them
well with your broker
I don't trade on I see markets anymore
okay I don't often
when when I'm going long
it could take up to 300 milliseconds
to fill my trade so I'm sitting there
sitting there sitting there sit and there
because normally when you click buy
you get you get your instant
it's almost instantaneous
you've been filled
when I click by
I wait
all I see is this circle
going round and round
around around around
around
waiting for my order
to get filled
yeah
when I see markets
they can't handle
the flow
so yeah
I trade on Saxo Bank
now
and Saxo Bank
is so much better
aren't they thinking
on their leverage
or
yeah it's 25 to 1 leverage
but you don't need
a lot of leverage
you
well it depends
on your account balance
doesn't it really
yeah yeah but in reality you you shouldn't be trying to flip money in effects
is the way I see it you should initially start out as a person who's trying to make
an income and consistent money from the market and then over time you can identify the right
opportunity the right environment to risk a bit more and then you can try to flip money
yeah that's the end result where you're with your experienced enough to identify the
correct stuff and then you can identify you know take on that risk I long
it when you read them as here
stop here so it's quite a wide stop
but we're up and let me have a look
probably about 10 15 pills
fair enough so that's some
light change fever
that pumps me up to
how many hours is that
six I'm on 13 pips
that's a bit dead
yeah volume is a bit thingy at the moment isn't it
you still see it like going up
we should go to 29
we should go to there but obviously
doesn't mean it well
Anyway, going back to this stuff
They won't take you one as a client
Your broker, your broker externalizes your trades
Sorry, internalizes your trade
It takes the risk against you
Okay, so some of the takeaways from here
Each bank is quite a bit enough
A bit of that's price, a bit of that price, bit of ask price
Remember how I said, third-party non-bank market makers
Start to access EBS and they then also
started to provide equity themselves, become market makers.
And they provided more competitive quotes.
So 0.2 pips, for example, spread.
Now, you've been talking about a small hedge fund,
a retail broker who is too small to be accepted by a bank
as a prime brokerage client.
They just simply can't go to a bank and say,
do you want to trade with you directly, et cetera, et cetera.
Because liquidity is so fragmented,
look, you can get liquidity here or here,
or here, or here, about 10 other venues.
or multiple non-bank market makers,
which one do you choose?
It's all broken into pieces, yeah?
Yeah.
That created demand for aggregators.
So you have these third-party firms,
like EBS, basically,
that connect everybody together.
What they will do is they'll take all the bid-and-ask,
bid-and-ask, bid-and-ask from all the banks,
all the liquidity providers,
aggregate it all up into an order book like this.
So this is what Sachsler Bank does.
They are a hope.
All right. So if we look at this, this is GDP, UST now 0.8b spread. Can you see this? Yeah, no. 300k there. Just 200. Yeah. All right. So this liquidity is coming from multiple banks here and here. It's not just one, it's not just one liquidity provider. Do you get it? Yeah.
Saxo Bank will be connected to one, two, three, four, five, six, seven different. Saxo Bank has a prime brokerage relationship with these banks. All right?
And it'll be connected to the actual interbank market itself and other third party non-bank market makers.
If you're looking at their box, it'll be looking at how much the equity they're offering.
You'll be looking at their prices and aggregating it all up into this best bid, best offer.
So you can access such a tight quote there.
And then obviously, Saxo Bank is selling these services onto retail brokers.
So think about it.
Like I said, retail broker cannot access the bank as a prime brokerage client.
But Saxo Bank is a firm.
which knows
that retail brokers
need prime brokerage
so these guys
already have a connection
with the bank
they then resell it
as something called
prime of prime
so these guys are
prime brokers
these guys are prime
of prime of prime
and these guys
do provide prime
brokerage services
to retail brokers
to smaller firms
to more riskier firms
okay
small hedge firms
so in other words
when your retail broker
wants to start
providing liquidity
to you
let it just pull it out their house
they need
they need liquidity from the banks.
They can approach a firm like Saxo Bank,
access prime brokerage services from them.
Saxo Bank will let them build a private liquidity pool
that takes prices from Bank 1, Bank 2, Bank 3, Bank 4, etc., etc.
It will refine it for them.
It will structure it for them.
It will provide all these services like an off-shelf type option,
like a package, like a holiday package.
So the retail broker firm goes to Saxo Bank,
gets prime brokerage, accesses liquidity from the banks
through Saxo
and effectively
all the infrastructure
is all ready to go
Saxo Bank will provide
the risk management engine
so it will
it will be all automated
that allows the broker
to A book B or B or Q
the broker doesn't have to do it themselves
they can set the parameters
from a computer
on the engine
that Saxo Bank is given them
it will also come up with the trading engine
so who matches the trades together
how does
so when a client of
let's say Zane
he goes along with IC markets
well IC marks has to fill that order
that order goes onto this trading engine
that will either match it off internally
if you're a B-bucked or it will
externalize the trade into the market so it's all
automated these all this
infrastructure is set up already
mainly by these technology firms
that act as aggregators
and Saxo Bank will also be aggregating
on the best best offers similar to how they do here
okay now
with a private liquidity pool
you can take a bank
out, you can include a bank, you can include a HFC firm, which will give you super, super
tight spreads, but lesser liquidity at top of block. That's why if you ever see on IC markets
a 0.1 piped spread for GVUST, it's 100% because they are sourcing prices from a HFT
firm, which acts as a market maker. They're going to be giving them on a zero fucking
pip spreads. So what about like EU as well? Is that like literally the same?
same, because that's usually like zero.
Bro, EU, you can have a positive
spread on that. Oh, really?
You can have a positive spread on that,
but EU is always tied to them in GDP, USD.
Yeah, yeah. All these currency pairs are the same.
All the major pairs at these stock is so much tire
because it's more liquid.
Yeah, a firm like IC Markets,
this is what they do.
They have a prime broker called CFH clearing.
CFH is connected to all the global banks.
IC Marcus will have instructed CFH
to build the amount of liquidity pool
so that's just say they have bank one
two, three, three and four
and the HFT firm
and also
yeah, right
and the HFT firm
that's going to be taking the best best offer
making a single price for it
and obviously a order book
that ICMarkis can see
as the market can see that
what IC markets does is they take that
exact price as it is and give it to you
but when you go longer that price
they do not send it out to the market
they just take the trade against you
on the prices being set by the banks
it's like
it's like me going into pound shop
finding out the price of a fucking sweets
and then going outside the pound shop
and selling the same suite to everybody else
at the same price
okay you get it
yeah yeah that's what I see markets do
now some brokers like
IG for example
they'll be getting the prices
from their liquidity provider
and let's say the best bid
best offer they can access
has a zero pip spread
they will give it to you
adding on a zero
adding on let's say one pip spread
so when they have actually
a zero pip spread
they're going to be giving you
a best bid best offer
that is wider than what they can access
that's how they capture in the spread
okay yeah so that's their model
on making money
isn't it?
They're marking up the spread.
So you come to me, you want to buy some drugs.
I go through my friend, I give it back to our markup.
So I buy it for $200, I sell it to you for $220.
I marked it up.
You're going to IG to buy liquidity.
IG is sourcing it from the market.
They have the necessary relationships and the infrastructure.
They're paying for it, basically.
And in return for that, they obviously charge you and mark the volume up.
Oh, sorry, market the liquidity up.
In other case, they still trade against you.
So this is essentially what's happening.
Now, to give you insight to what these third-party firms are,
one of them is Koronex, another one is hotspot,
another one is FX-all, another one is...
But there's a few of them.
Now, finally, what I'll say is,
when the banks were fighting back to avoid posting liquidity on EBS,
what EBS is classed as a third-party aggregator now as well.
Initially, it was just for banks,
and then it started giving access
to third-party non-banks
so it also became an aggregator
think about it
when a bank chooses
to post liquidity on EBS
they are posting their orders
on an outside venue
right and they task in the order handling
to that venue the venue handles the orders
why would a bank do that
maybe EBS brings so much
much volume that the bank
simply can't ignore
trading on EBS
and providing liquidity
at EBS.
And this is effectively
what goes on with Kourinex hotspot,
FX all.
These are institutional platforms.
If you want to trade on it,
you need to have prime brokerage access
to the quotes that these banks
are posting on there.
But the third party
handles the order of execution.
It won't be a case of
the bank is deciding
to fill you or not.
If there's liquidity
on this third party platform
if the bank's post on there
then the third party platform
will handle the execution for you
it will make sure
it basically makes it a bit more transparent
it's like a referee again
it's slightly closer
to a centralised
try to tap the platform
all right
so these third party
firms
because FX liquidity is so fragmented
they felt the need
or there was a demand for aggregation
of all this liquidity
in 2020 what they effective
you do is the act as a supermarket. You can go to a supermarket. You can buy alcohol or you can buy
fucking fuck cream. Big, big variety of products available in the supermarket. These third-party
firms, they also have a very, very big variety of the types of liquidity and the types of services
they offer. They can offer liquidity to HFT firm. They can offer liquidity to small retail
brokerage. They can offer liquidity to small, medium-sized businesses that just need to do real money
transactions when they want to hedge risk because they're selling
Shisha Flavor to some Bush and ticket, right?
They can do any of this stuff.
They act as a supermarket and they don't necessarily, they're not providing liquidity.
They're just facilitating trade and provide them the necessary infrastructure,
the right organization of the markets to connect buys and sellers together.
This is where we're up with the market today.
Whilst the banks were posting liquidity and the banks do post liquidity on these third parties,
and most of these
like retail brokerage firms
they go through their prime broker
so IC Markets goes through CFH
clearance
CFH clearing
will work typically closely with one of these venues
and get some of the liquidity from there
they'll get some of the liquidity directly from the banks
and they all aggregate it up here
the bank also has
that's what you call sorry a multi-dealer platform
because it's a platform that FX all is running
It's literally a software that you can connect to.
It's a venue that you can join,
not you, but as an institutional client.
You can join that venue and access, obviously,
that platform that has multiple dealers on there,
competing against each other.
The banks invested heavily in their own technology to avoid EBS.
So they started, basically,
their offering for their clients was a single deal platform, right?
So when their clients wanted to deal directly with a bank,
because it's like the safety of a bank,
I can say a large corporation like Apple
or a large hedge fund for example
sorry a large pension fund for example
they can trade on the platform
that the bank makes through their own tech side
and just simply trade directly with a bank on the disclosed basis
rather than go to a multi-dealer platform
it's all options really
and just giving you insight the amount of options they have
you can trade directly with a bank
you can trade on a third-party venue
which has multiple banks competing against each other at
each of them have the pros and cons
which we can discuss at a later date
but effectively the one I'm saying is
FX market is now fragmented
it's broken into pieces
third-party venues
they take market share away from banks
and they run these institutional platforms
that aggregate equity
they provide multiple
multiple different types of services
and they create it to the slightly smaller
side of the market institutional
but smaller
okay all right and then banks have a single dealer platforms as well now believe it or not which
what do you think is better which type of model do you think is better dealing directly with the bank on
the single deal of platform training on the bank's prices as a client or dealing on a platform
that's an MDP multi-deal platform it makes bank one bank two bank three bank four bank five takes all
the prices gives you the best bid best offer it makes it more transparent execution
because a third party is handling it, not the bank.
The bank can't do questionable stuff,
like take a long time to fill your trade,
reject your trades as frequently
because the third party will punish them.
They oversee it like a referee.
Which models better?
The multi-dealer platform.
Still, the majority of volume by 2016
were trading through single-dealer platforms
because...
It's more safe, isn't it?
It's not because you're still trading
against the banks on the multi-dea platform.
what it is is most of the market in effects the demand for equity doesn't come from price sensitive traders
what i mean is when i'm a trader today i have to get tight spreads and good execution fast execution
instantaneous execution very very frequently persistent this is the type of environment that i'm
looking for yeah yeah but they don't need it do they they don't need it yeah the majority
of the volume and FX
it doesn't really need it
it didn't really need it slowly but surely
we are switching to a more transparent model
the banks are catering to that
now some of these banks
have formed a
just a fucking word bro
basically where banks come together and they have their own
multi-dealer platform
to get it
so the banks come together they have their own
multi-dealer platform
they're forming their own multi-deal platform
yeah okay
it's called
hot stream
or something like that.
It's owned by banks.
Corinex, which was originally
a private firm, is owned by
FX all is owned by routers.
EBS is now bought out by
CME, the exchange.
So you can just imagine what's going on.
They're all monopolize, all right?
It originally starts out with multiple firms
or started out as multiple firms, but now
some of these firms have died.
Some of these firms being brought out by larger firms
like CME is probably,
you know, you know, if there was
you know if Illuminati was real
I'd say CME is a fucking
Illuminati. That's how much power they have
that fucking ridiculous power
The Chicago Mercantile Exchange
They run the futures exchanges
Okay
Right
They're a fucking superpower of financial markets
Obviously banks are as well
It's all a fight for market share
They all provide services
Most of the money is made by providing services
during the gold rush where everybody was mining for gold
the real money was made by selling the spade
that's a quote
selling the spade yeah if you're mining gold
if I sell you the spade and everybody's crazy about mining gold
I'm selling spades to everybody
I make more money that way
and this is what these banks do
anyone that's a middleman kind of makes the most money
if you look at Uber
they charge you three pounds of fucking delivery if not more
if you look at
Airbnb which up until now was doing
super well
if you look anybody who's a middleman
they kick it similar to what these banks do
they don't have to be active in the market
is trading pound up
and pushing it because they're bullish on it
so yeah that's really
that's really
the effect structure as they exist today
banks internalize trades
a good good majority
that are internalized
volume less often goes
in trades on EBS
when you're trading directly with a bank
and even if like a bank is dealing with you
dealing to you on a multi-deal platform
so here's bank one bank two bank three bank four
imagine you're buying
this guy had the cheapest ask price
but you're still trading against the bank right
you bought the bank shorts against you
the bank ends up receiving that
even though it's filled on this third party
and they pay a small commission one or two dollars per million
the bank still shorted that risk against you
now the bank has to hedge the risk externally they have to match it in-house or they can just take the trade against you right
they still have even when you're basically with my making it even when it's a multi-nealer platform
they're still having to these these three options still apply right so is all of that done through like
machines and stuff then like high-tick it's all open yeah it's all amazing okay like i said
hFT firms came onto eBSs to exploit bank inefficiencies there were two
slow. H-fifty firms raped them.
So, obviously, banks initially would have been last luck in them.
They would have rejected their orders.
They would have quoted wider spreads.
The market would have become slightly more inefficient and volatile.
But the bank slowly but surely invested heavily in their own technology, in their own
capability to provide liquidity themselves on a fast basis to compete against this new,
new like man on the block.
So, yeah, they also developed.
their own tech side.
Like I said,
banking today is ruled
by technology
more than it is by
like smart
and savvy traders.
It's really just
super,
super geeky motherfuckers.
Yeah,
so technology is basically
everything in FX,
in all financial markets now.
It's everything.
It's made it more efficient.
It's given a speed advantage
to certain participants.
It's allowed these guys
to manage their risks
super, super well.
You know,
if you go long,
at price one
and then everybody else goes long at price one
and the bank is short at price one
they're fucked
they're not making money anymore
they need to be able to manage that risk
they need to be able to see
price changes before everybody
they need to be able to get out positions
before everybody
obviously they already have advantages
but having this technological speed advantage of everyone
it puts them in this like type
of top percentile of the market
where it's almost impossible for these guys
to lose money
the only reason
I can imagine that banks
would not make that much money from FX
is because of the
more to do with the regulatory side
the type of operations and the type of
money they have to invest in overseeing
that the media and regulatory
Mondays and stuff
checking all transactions
or report in X many transactions
and hiring people to go through
that's going to be the most costly side of things
not the actual training side
but even retail
brokers, when they buy an off-shelf-type packages and the trading engine fills the trades
for them, all they have to have is one or two motherfuckers overseeing the computer, making
sure that everything's running nicely, whilst the good majority of the retail broker,
like workforce would be focused on sourcing new clients, so sales force, and then
regulatory. So, like, if the retail broker is giving the proper,
advice or selling, you know, if the execution policy is correct, all this kind of stuff
is going to be the most costly thing for a retail broker, next to maintaining the relationship
with the prime broker, that's where most of the cost go.
Actually, today, the technology is everything's all, it's all snap, it's all done for you,
you can just go buy it and, yeah, anyway, moving on, we're going to look at how a bank
can internalize trade
because the majority of flow
when you trade against a bank
or when a client trades against a bank
when a broker trades against a bank,
majority that flow
the bank internalizes
to keep it in-house
because for two reasons
they want to avoid
obviously the information leakage
but also
nobody knowing that the bank
has taken on a position
gives them more time and space
to manage that risk
and I'll let you go
this is going to be the last session really
before we go on the price
oh okay
so this will be like
microstructure done then
it will remain a theme
always
yeah yeah yeah
yeah because obviously
you said that
this is where the edge
this is why price behaves
the way it does
we're trying to find edge
so we use this as a way
to try and make sense of prices
or identify edge
you get it
yeah
so it's critical
because look
back in 20
back in 2002
if you were trading
you would have wider spreads
number one number two
the way of having more adverse volatility
and the way we'll come to
find is you like the way we trade at least
is favorable for low
volatility environments which is probably
70% of the market.
Equities, so stocks
equities basically
indexes
I guess 5100
currencies a good 70%
of the time they're low volatile.
Nothing's happened.
You know how I said
that most of the volume is from
participants who are non-speculative
and how like as
Apple you will need liquidity on both
in Japan, Japanese, yen, basically globally
you need FX liquidity.
All right.
Currency is tied to almost every transaction.
So if that's the case,
it makes FX unique
in the fact that
everybody needs the pound,
everybody needs the US dollar as well.
Right? So we can
almost always expect it to be
buyers for the US dollar and buyers for the pound almost always you will have two-sided
liquidity let me validate that point for you if we look at a weekly chart all fx markets do
barring event-driven environments like a like a financial crisis or like Brexit outside of those
scenarios all markets do in fx is find value and range between these it basically range there's buyers here
the sellers here we can consistently rely on the high level of natural demand for effects liquidity
to create buyers and sellers on both sides of the market unless of course you're trading something
like shit like turkish lira then nobody wants to buy a turkish lira nobody wants to do business
for turkey or like if you're fucking trading north korean whatever it is you're a fucking idiot then
but major currencies which are tied to global trade how fx is integral to global trade
in a globalized economy, you know, with multinational globalized businesses,
you are always going to have liquidity on both sides of the market.
FX is dominated by, for operational reasons,
in terms of where the liquidity comes from,
rather than speculators trying to push it up and down.
Don't get me wrong, they are speculators here.
We can consistently see for the last 10 years people have brought the US dollar
and large firms have brought US dollar over the pound for the last 10 years.
from 2008, all the way to pretty much now.
Now, that being said,
just because the sellers and speculative sellers in the market
does not mean that they are always selling,
that's two completely different things.
One is if something exists,
and the other is intensity.
The intensity of selling of speculators,
for the most part, is not aggressive.
They only become aggressive under certain environments.
Other than that, what they've done is they've waited for this price and built up a huge position here.
And then there was an event in 2014 where basically the US dollar appreciated for something called a carry trade.
And then after that event, like the intensity of that event, like tapered off.
It was less intense.
The market stopped caring about it.
Again, the market stabilized.
And again, those aggressive traders who traded aggressively for a period of time went back to the normal type of trading,
which is building positions over time
in line with a macro view
rather than aggressively pushing the market in a single direction.
So what I'm talking to you here is
they smacked it here, they smacked it here, they smacked it here
rather than driving, driving, driving, driving.
The effect of that is the price, for the most part,
we can expect it to be a more of a passive,
slower, less aggressive, speculative effect
basically creating an environment of two side of liquidity.
If there's liquidity on both sides,
if I said to you, there's bi-liquity here, sell liquidity here,
the probability and that liquidity is coming from multiple sources,
not necessarily speculators all the time.
It could be just a very, very large transaction
because a corporation is doing something.
It could be a large pension fund filtering and hedging off some risks
that they've built up for whatever reason.
It could be a hedge fund filtering some, hedging some currency risk, right?
None of those reasons are speculative.
In either case, that liquidity basically can support prices consistently.
We can consistently expect price to stop there because, like we know, the market to limit order ratio is what drives prices.
If the behaviors of the speculators in FX is passive, i.e., they don't try to trade.
They're more price sensitive.
So they don't trade on urgent orders.
They wait for their prices to build positions at certain prices.
If that's the case, there'll be less of a driving effect, more of a ranging effect.
If we're consistently seeing a large buyer's happen here, the sellers will, whenever price reaches down there,
the market order selling will not be intense enough to push past it.
all right unless for example let's say three major hedge funds in the world built up a long position
because they were earning the interest for owning the pound over from 2001 all the way to 2008
so they built up a very big long position now in 2008 it was a credit crunch basically when
before that they were looking to make money after the credit crunch they're looking to
save money not even make money anymore just to keep it safe so they started to get out of
out of their long position.
How do you go as a long position, you short it.
Now, in this event, there's a high level of urgency to get out as quick as possible,
so they market order to sell it.
And we'll discuss the dynamic here, which basically turns into that self.
We'll discuss what happens here, right?
But you can just imagine there's a lack of high liquidity, it's heavy selling going on
because it's a high level of urgency.
And then once that urgency is done, the market then stabilizes again.
The volume, the heavy, heavy sell volume dries off.
The liquidity comes back into the market.
Still, corporations need to transact.
Still, hedge funds need to hedge their risk.
Still, you know, people are going to start taking out loans from banks
and there's going to be cross-border transactions, et cetera.
Did you get it?
That side of FX, that demand, the natural level of demand for FX never goes away.
So once the urgency is over, and once there's obviously a response to the urgency,
nobody's certain and nobody wants to trade in huge amounts
and during these periods.
So if there's heavy, heavy selling going on,
nobody wants to be a buyer.
So imagine this is what happens.
Something happens that great
that makes me uncertain.
Okay, that's one thing.
And then price starts doing this.
That makes me even more uncertain,
making me less likely to trade.
And then obviously it's hitting some people to sell stops,
increasing the selling intensity,
increasing the volatility
making me more nervous
so it results in this very, very
very aggressive time scenario
similar to a flash crash.
A flash crash is just simply this
a million times worse.
Do you get it?
Yeah, by a million what I mean is this happened over weeks.
Flash crash would do it in a single day.
Right? Because that is
algorithms heavy wiring. It's definitely
hitting cell stops. So there's a whole
bunch of selling going on. Algo is
not place them by liquidity in, rather the alga is aggressively trying to beat each other
in capturing whatever liquidity is available. So put it this way. Imagine you have two HFT
algos. One HFT algos brought here, sorry, sold here. There was bi-liquity from Al-Go
two. And then Al-Go 1 has now shorter there, so Al-Go 1 places bi-liquity here. Get it.
Can you explain that again? I didn't quite understand that bit.
all right so
imagine
you have two algorithms
I'll go one
I'll go two
yeah
Algo two
managed to go short here
at Algo 1's
by limit order
he captured it
he got it
yeah
and then Algo 1 is short
he decides to
get out of that position
here
and plays to some
buy liquidity
at a lower price
Algo 1 has made money
yeah
he's short here
buys it back there
yeah
Algo 2
sells there
he now is a short
position
he has to buy it back
he places by liquidity here
Algo 2 places by liquidity here
Algo 1 captures that
Now Algo 1 is short
He buys it back at a lower price
Algo 2 captures that
That's literally a flash crash
That's literally what's happening
In a flash crash
This is called wash trading
Algo is a trading between themselves
Capturing the liquidity
Trying to chase it
Whilst there's hardly any real liquidity
in the market
And simultaneously sell stops are being hit
Sell stops on market order sales
basically when they get hit.
Yeah, okay.
So there's a whole bunch of selling going on.
There's a whole bunch of alga that's competing against each other
and selling to each other time and time and time again,
wash trading,
and there's hardly any by liquidity in the market.
Flash flashes, that's why they dump thousands of pips within minutes.
Wow.
Obviously, that's on the super, super extreme end.
This is still on the extreme end,
and this is more natural trading.
You still have light sell liquidity here and buying going on.
You still have buy liquidity moving higher and higher,
but it's less intense and more stable and more efficient
than something like an event-driven state
where there's mass uncertainty,
everybody's, this huge, huge cell volume, et cetera, et cetera.
So outside of these environments, they never last that long.
Price typically goes back into this more passive state
with liquidity and the large traders who do take,
traditional views. They don't trade aggressively. They trade passive view with limit orders.
So we can consistently expect, we can basically trade both sides of the market. I've got 70%
at the time. And if I show you what cable's done for the last two weeks, it's exactly that.
So this is about three weeks ago. There's one week, about two weeks, and this is this third
week. Down up, down, down, down. Sell liquidity there, buy liquidity there. There's not a lot of
sell there's not a lot of volume pushing aggressively in a direction here that period was there
but most of the time price stable price is stable you know this move up it's not that aggressive
oh yeah became super aggressive here okay all right that's the type of um that's unique about
effects there's two-sided liquidity because it's a high level of natural demand for fx liquidity
anyway um okay here we're looking at an instance where a bank receives a large order you have to
remember banks are competing against each other yeah yeah imagine i'm a prime brokerage client a bank
one has a big price at price too so he's willing to buy there i can sell there and bank one
has a that's back that's one bank and another bank bank 15 has a offer at price one i can buy here
and immediately sell to that bid of there one of these banks fucked up now so put it this way
imagine bank one bank two bank three bank four bank five they all had a bid price at two two two two
two and the ask price was at three three three three yeah where can you buy here just oh they're
three yeah our price three and you can sell a price too yeah but bank 15 bank 15's got offer
ask price that price one he's failed to update his prices yeah i have because you're a prime brokerage
client, you can access all the banks liquidity, you can buy here immediately and immediately
sell to any of these banks at the real price and capture that difference.
So banks have a huge vested interest to keep the prices the same, especially since the rise
of prior brokerage and especially since they more, especially more since they internalize
most of their volume.
Do you get it?
If not, sophisticated clients will try to exploit this.
and efficiencies.
I would, right?
There's going to be clients.
If a bank is failing to keep the same prices
relative to all the other banks,
they will get exploited.
So again, they invested heavily
and their pricing engine side
to keep prices the same,
run the internalizing orders,
to keep it in line with all the other banks.
So if Bank one moves their prices higher,
Bank five also has to move the prices higher
in order to avoid selling cheap liquidity.
Do you get it?
So we can look at an example where Bank 5 chooses to internalize trades,
which is typically how trades are filled.
Flows are relatively stable across the market, yeah?
Here's Bank 1, Bank 2, Bank 3, Bank 4, Bank 5, by 6, Bank 7.
Bank 5's client, a private brokerage client goes long, let's just, for example, say, $500 million, right?
Bank of 5 has a simple task.
They just received a long order for $500 million.
They need to fill it.
They can go short against him, fine.
They'll never go short for $500 million in a single clip,
especially if they receive that order electronically.
What they will most likely do is they might have in their own order box.
So we're looking at this bank's own order box itself
because they internalize them the trade.
They might have some sell equity there,
some sell equity there, some sell equity there, some sell equity there, some sell equity there.
Why would they have sell equity there?
let's say I'm the other client
I have a sell limit order here
you have a sell limit order there
because we don't all take trades based off market orders
I could be a corporate client of the bank
who wants to trade at this price
X amount a million
and the bank can see that information
can see that liquidity sitting in a book
because I'm their client you get it
so the bank is tasked with
fill in this 500 million order
they will typically split into small pieces
to avoid destabilizing the market
so in other words you imagine
they had to find a 500 million seller one-to-one to fill that buyer.
The 500 million seller might be massively above price.
Rather than filling it up there,
they could just split this 500 million to small chunks,
tens, 20s, 30s, 40s, and fill it as price travels higher,
finding liquidity in the book.
Yeah.
You get it.
Now, once that's happening, what's just, what's going on?
Bank five has started to move his ask price.
because he's this 500 million is buying you always buying the ask price yeah bank five is what's he
doing behind the ask price what is what is the ass price this sell liquidity there theoretically yeah
the bank is giving the ask price to everybody to all their clients so behind that what
you're saying is at this price we're offering you let's say a million yeah so a 500 million
order comes in at the bank's
ask price where there's a million sitting there
obviously the bank will fill in for that million
the bank is short one million now
simultaneously
there's 499 left
the bank is very unlikely to want to go short against that
so rather than continuing
to fill them at the ask price
the bank holds the ask price higher
trying to match it with a set limit order
in the book
you get it
yeah yeah
So I have a sell limit order here.
So it'll raise it up until there.
Say again.
So it will raise the ass price up until there.
Yeah, raise the ass price, raise the ass price, raise the ass price up until here.
Essentially making this 500 million market order along, chase it.
Okay.
Right?
So it matches some there.
And then it pulls it higher again, matches there, matches there, matches it there.
And don't get a twisted, these banks, because they're so large,
because they have such a highly sophisticated network of clients,
they're very, very liquid, is what I'm saying.
Their own internal book is very, very liquid.
When that 500 million order came in initially,
the bank might have already had a position of 200 million long,
so they can immediately sell to him 200 million.
Obviously, they might spread it out,
and it's their discretion where they filter that volume out behind their ask price,
they control how much liquidity
to put behind the ask price
they want to keep the clients happy
they don't want to give them like
fucked up execution so they never come back again
so they have a direct interest
in sourcing them the best execution
they're not evil
they have to keep their clients
even if they are evil they have to keep their clients
yeah so
the bank's doing its job basically
source and equity in house
if the bank was to externalize
that trade and reveal that
500 million is being brought
all these good things
guys could exploit it and basically make the end fill, the final fill price, more expensive
for the client anyway. So it's better that the bank internalizes the trade. Now, once
this is happening, let's look at a time series of events. Order received here, that's the first
event. Bank accepts the order, that's second event. Bank starts to fill the order and moves
his ask price higher. That's the third event. As that first price,
ticket moves higher, that's new
information for all
these other banks that are
keeping, that need to keep
their quotes in line with every other bank.
Because like I said, if
these guys fail, if
these guys fail to keep their quotes in line,
think about it, Bank Five has now
moved his bid price and ask price
higher, right?
Yeah. Imagine you could sell there
and immediately buy
off the bank four, which failed to move his
ask price higher as well. Yeah.
That would be a big exploitation.
You can exploit, yeah.
So basically, these bank four, bank five,
they all employ infrastructure to keep prices the same,
especially in these moving markets when prices are moving.
So if one bank starts to adjust their prices higher,
it kind of triggers that mechanism across all the rest of the banks
to keep prices the same and start also reflecting those same prices.
This is a very, very unique thing.
Because think about it, if Bank Five moved from price
5 to 5.1 to 5.2 to 5.3 where there was a sell limit order. That sell limit order had 20 million
behind it. So what's happened? 500 million. One million is filled at the first price. It skips
price one, price two and it goes to price three to find 20 million. Yeah? Yeah. So how much is left
over here? 479. You get it? What is bank for it triggers its mechanism to keep prices
the same to maintain price
stability. Bank 4
then starts to move. When
Bank 5 was at price 0.1,
Bank 4 was also at price 0.1.
When Bank 5 is at
price 0.2, Bank 4 is also
at price 0.2.
When Bank 5 is at price 0.3, it's
also at price 0.3.
They're not copying each other.
They're doing it at the same time, essentially.
Okay. Even the
slightest inefficiency,
even the slightest slowness
here from Bank 4 can be exploited
by predatory type
participants. So you can just imagine
it's super fast. But what we're reaching
here is like this problem.
Imagine you
you as
a client of Bank 4 had
a sell liquidity of 20 million
at the first price.
What's the problem here?
You have a sell order here for 20 million.
Bank 5 is a lot of to move
from price 1, bank 2 to price 3.
right
like four also has to move from price one
price two to price three
triggering your 20 million order yeah
yes it's not the way it's favor
no no but
you're selling to a bank here
think about you're selling to the bank there
do they offer that sell liquidity out
to their clients
does bank four offer your sell liquidity out
behind the ask price
no
why because if they did
whilst bank five has already moved
to price three, there's 20 million worth of sell equity in the way here that their clients have
to buy before price can move through.
Stopping Bank 4 from moving.
Yeah.
If they offered that 20 million sell equity to you as their client, sorry, to another as their
client, they have a wall of friction and resistance here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Whilst Bank 5 has already pushed higher, instant.
things. So in order to stop the from happening, your order will get filled. The bank will take
the risk against you. Okay. They have a high level of certainty that price will continue going
up. They can go long here. And that's the only way they can continue to reflect the same
prices as Bank Five, right? And simultaneously now, Bank Four has just gone long for 20 million.
They don't have an inventory of 20 million long. So if any clients want to sell to Bank Four,
If they want to sell here at the same price that the Bitter that the Bank 5 has, Bank 4 has $20 million worth to buy back off their clients.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Are you following me?
They can provide the equity on the way up.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Sorry, if the clients want to buy, what we're talking about, if the clients want to buy,
bank has already bought $20 million, they can sell it to their clients.
Yeah, because they know that it's going to keep going up so they can.
no no no that's not what I'm saying
I'm saying
bank five moves their price is higher
they're trying to find liquidity at these horizontal
red lines that triggers bank four
he needs to keep prices the same
he has liquidity at different
horizontal red lines
if this liquidity is offered out to the market
to his own clients
these are the prices that have to be taken
for price to continue going in local
okay
think about it
if there was a hundred million here
how much buying has to happen
for price to go up past this
first red line. Yeah, that's to be quite a bit.
How much?
100 million.
Exactly.
So one of Bank 4's clients has to bid 100 million
for price to go to the next level.
If Bank 4 offered that 100 million
out to its clients.
Whilst this is happening,
Bank 5's already jumped to this price.
Instantaneously, because that's where there's liquidity
in their own book. Can you see the prices
are broken apart again? Yeah.
So to stop that happening,
Bank 4 has to control
the supply of equity. There's 100
million available sell liquidity there. They have to control
it. They can't give it to the market.
They have to take the opposite side, so go long.
Now they've brought 100
million.
As price goes up
on Bank 4's book, because
they keep in the same price as Bank 5,
imagine it hits people's buy stops, which is
more buying. So other clients,
start buying with bank four as well bank four has to sell to them yeah well he has a hundred
million to sell to them now oh yeah okay you get it yeah yeah yeah so the point i'm raising here is
if you look at it on from an objective point of view in reality there was plenty of there was a
hundred million worth of liquidity here that bank four should have been able to give to bank five's
client to give it a slightly cheaper execution cost yeah
But what he, you know, he should have offered a hundred million out.
But what actually happened is, that motherfucker didn't give it to anybody.
He kept it for himself.
The result, again, less liquidity available in the market, causing prices to travel further to find liquidity.
So the whole point is, when there's a fast-mover market and these guys have to keep prices the same, because they're going to have liquidity at different levels, they have to control the supply of liquidity.
Now, think about it.
The market is there to facilitate trade.
So if they sell liquidity there, I should be able to.
able to get it if the market's doing this job well.
But in this environment, there was sell liquidity there.
The clients could not get that sell liquidity at the price that it should be given at.
That's an inefficiency.
That's an example of how the market is not doing a shop as well as it should because of, again, participant behavior, the way banks are behaving.
Now, the effect of that is what?
If there's less liquidity being given to the market and actually exists, what was the effect?
price has to travel further to find it exactly price volatility increases now that's one that's one thing secondly
these banks are not necessarily copying each other's prices it's more like a horse race
right so initially this 500 million drove prices higher at bank five it triggered these guys
like protection mechanisms and they started to pull their ass prices higher
So when volumes coming in, because people's buy stops are being hit,
loads of the clients are coming in long, for example, let's say.
These banks, they typically want to avoid going short in this environment, right?
Because prices continue to go up.
Now, this is how they control the supply of liquidity.
If volumes coming up are any of these banks, basically,
they're always trying to price slightly more expensive than each other.
So if this guy is pricing at 0.01, this guy's trying to price at 0.001, 0.01 more expensive.
Right? So think about it. When the volume is coming in, it's now not driving price. It's not driving the ask price anymore. It's chasing the ask price.
The ask price is running away from the buy volume chasing after it.
Rather than, rather than the buy volume driving the ask price higher looking for sell liquidity, is now to turn.
under this dynamic of Aspriced running away.
So it causes the buy volume to seek after it, jump after it,
stretch after it, basically.
So initially, the buy volume would start out like this.
The buy volume would start off like this, super, super thick.
More buying steps in here from another client.
More buy stops that hit there.
More buying comes in here.
And everybody starts to buy.
You know what I mean about buy stops, yeah?
Yeah, yeah.
If you have a short position, you have a buy stop loss.
If you hit that buy stop loss,
one is too little cell liquidity already,
more banks happening.
It will drive price.
And because of this price,
the mechanism kicking off,
the banks triggering this protection mechanism
and pulling the ask prices high,
pulling the sell equity away from buyers,
controlling the amount of sell equity they provide anyway,
this buy volume now has to stretch a bit.
And it stretches.
and it gets stretches and it stretches and it stretches and it stretches until by the end of it
this original 500 million and whatever other buying came through has either been cancelled
because of the inefficient nature of basically this this 500 million is now stretching too far
it doesn't want to transact anymore enough for themselves yeah reaching for the cells which are not
present so it cancelled if there are certain risk management tools that clients have
where they can't cancel orders or pause orders if the volatility conditions are too high.
Or the order gets filled.
So it's been stretched.
It's been stretched.
They've been stretched.
They've filled 50, 10, 20, da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da.
It's all been filled now.
Or it's finally reached the area.
So 500, 20, 60, has 100, 160, has another 100, 260, et cetera, yeah, until it's only like 40 million
buying left and it's finally reached the area where there's a day.
decent amount of sell liquidity.
The buying dries off.
The sellers absorb it.
What's left behind is a very, very thinly traded area
of prices. It ran further than
it showed. The sell liquidity
was not given to the market as
it should have been. These guys' behaviours
of adjusting their ass prices made it worse.
Pulled the volume
higher, stretched it out. Left behind is vacuum.
Yeah, it draws back in.
It creates that. Now,
any volume that comes in
is enough to push price down because
there's such a weakness on the bits.
No buy liquid.
Even if there was, let's just say there was one order of $500 million that drove price higher.
That's a market order, yeah?
Yeah.
What about the other buy limit orders that would have been down here?
Let's just say there was 600 million of worth of buy limit orders that were down here at the time that this market order by a push price up.
Yeah.
Theoretically, theoretically those buyers could move up and hold.
and basically buy liquidity here.
What does that mean then if that was a case?
Wouldn't it react off that?
Yeah.
If the 600 million buy liquidity accepted and moved higher...
Yeah, there'd be a reaction from there.
And price would then stabilise here.
There wouldn't be weakness on a buy liquidity then, would there?
Yeah, no.
But because these dislocations are a function of liquidity providers
pulling the volume higher and stretching it out,
it's not really a market decision
the market isn't deciding
to push price up this aggressively
rather the behavior of the dealers
is causing price to pull out and stretch out
so whilst this is happening
the real liquidity from
the clients the trading
the trading desire
remains back down here
this stretch out
it's just more dislocation
it's a fragmentation
of the real value from the market
the reason the price is fragmented and dislocated
from the true area of by liquidity is because the dealers are pulling the volume higher,
they're avoiding providing liquidity, they're all going into protective mode.
So again, the behaviours of these dealers are creating these super, super over-pronounced moves
because of their behaviours.
And the rest of the market, you still wanted to trade down here.
I'll give you an example of how this could be made better.
Remember how there was 100 million here?
Yeah.
And it was 20 million there.
Imagine this guy had 100 million.
This guy had 100 million.
And all of these guys were on a single order book.
And the clients could access that single order book.
Then Bank 5 would never have internalized the trade and pulled it higher to this 20 million just to keep the information in-house.
It would only be one house rather than seven different houses.
So all this 100 million.
200, 300 million
would be aggregated
and it probably would have got
filled over a few prices
Yeah, instead of reaching so far up
Because then, you know, exactly
So this is an example about
Rather than initially it was
EBS and hot potato trading
causing price to drive higher
And now is these guys
hiding information from each other
So the only information
They have is each other's prices
So the effect is always the same
The whole point behind this is
humans by nature are irrational.
We do irrational shit.
The rational kind of source
course of action would be
for all the liquidity to fucking congregate in one single venue
and to regulate how,
to regulate the practices of speedy type traders.
It's really cheating.
If you're paying for really expensive data feeds
and if you have the capacity to trade on a sub-second basis
and explore everybody else in illegal ways,
it's fucking cheating bro you should regulate that shit
but it's not regulated or the regulations
aren't on implemented as well as it shouldn't be
these guys are rent seeking so they're trying to keep
market share for themselves without creating new market share
they're just trying to keep it as it is
so they're important super questionable practices
so it creates these inefficiencies in the market
now I'm not complaining because
these inefficiencies are creating this skewed bucket environment
where there's weak bids, thick a cell liquidity.
The cell liquidity is thick.
I can expect it to be thick
because it's a high level of natural demand
for sell liquidity and buy liquidity.
It's only this middle period,
middle part of that price run
that was created as a result
of these guys' behaviours.
So the buys are thick down there,
the sellers are thick up there,
the liquidity provider creates weakness in the middle.
I like that.
That inefficiency gives me edge.
So this is kind of the whole basis
behind what we're going to be trading.
This is the structure
will be looking at. Price Jason mechanism triggered after volume comes in. Thin liquidity left behind
is classed as inefficient trading because not a lot of selling is happening. It leaves behind
this void. At the end of this price run it becomes super, super jump. All right. So we're going to see
price become, this is called the sideways and the parabolic phase. After that is called the apex.
Then it's called the shelf flip. And it's called the bearish-filled flow.
And this is what you call a shift in the state of liquidity.
So there was bi-liquity here.
There's a shift in the state of liquidity.
The bi-liquity disappears.
And the same thing occurs on the way down.
And then the side of this pop again.
Now, you might ask, how is the bi-liquity there?
If this is a void, we'll discuss it.
Basically, some liquidity in real example.
So this move could be one pip, it could be 50-p.
when it's like a 30-p-p, 40-pip, 50-pip move,
it's not just one example of sell equity running away
and a huge order of pushing and pushing and pushing.
It's actually composed when it's a larger move.
It's made up of multiple of these.
So it's pop really, really inefficient,
volume dries off, leaves behind a void,
and price stabilizes again.
And pops and stabilizes again.
parts stabilizes again that's how 50 60 70 higher you know bigger distance moves are made up
it's not just a wave of consistent and constant sorry it's not just a wave of constant
buying buying buying buying sellers running away sellers running away sellers running away and the larger
moves okay so uh in the larger moves basically what i'm saying is you'll have some buy liquidity
left over at this last range right and when that breaks you get that shift you follow me
but in the in the super super like lower time frame micro volatility moves
the bank is completely avoiding so you know providing liquidity there's one volume shot
is 10 million it comes at the right time with the liquidity provider does not want to take
short positions so he removes sell liquidity all the other guys remove sell equity and pull
pull the buy volume higher it can result in like a 30 second period a 20 second period
where there's only buying hardly any selling going on
and price just pop in one time.
I'll give you an example of that.
So here is one of those higher time frame moves
where it's composed of multiple pops, multiple pops stability,
pop stability, pop stability, pop stability, pop stability.
As you can imagine, it's in this pop,
it's in this pop, it's in this pop,
where the bank price chasing mechanism,
the protection mechanism is triggered, it's running hot.
But obviously it slows down,
the volume dries off
price comes down
picks up the buy
liquidity again
and goes again
so it does it on a repeated basis
broadly speaking
this is the weak sell liquidity
but it's not like
there's no
sell liquidity there
yeah
compare that to
this
where it would have just
have been one volume shot
absolutely hardly
any sell liquidity there
and price just went
smack bang
bomb
did you get it
yeah
so the same thing
this is more intense
this is a single condition
whereas larger moves are made up of multiple of those
are you following me
so it's made up of multiple of these
stability volume surge
triggers the protection mechanism
everybody avoid all the deals avoid selling
and price chases the sell liquidity
the market so let's just say that was a 10 million by order
fills 1 million 2 million 3 million
the last 7 million is filled here
at this pocket of cell liquidity
the 10 million buying is done
left behind a whole void
of buyers, hardly any buying done
any light selling that comes in
is able to push prices down
in this instance
we're seeing buyers
accept higher and higher and higher and higher
prices for a sustained period
so what happens is price pops
dries off stabilises
fills that thinness stabilizes
pops
dries off stabilizes fills that weakness
pops each one of those pops
is volume coming in consistently.
It's not coming in constantly.
It's not pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop.
Nobody's sitting there and buying,
billion after billion after billion after billion after billion,
rather it happens in like cycles.
You have stability, surge, price stabilizes.
Nobody wants to buy up there anymore
because of the level of inefficiency.
Price slowly stabilizes and draws down.
The volume dries off, and then the volume kicks.
syn again. So that's how large moves are composed, but this structure, it applies equally to this
whole move as well, because still relative to how much transactions were formed here, let's
just say there was 10 billion transacted there, there would still be a relatively thinner
amount here. So there might only be 1 billion, 1.5, et cetera, et cetera. This is still a lot of
selling, but relatively
thinner to the origin.
Yeah. Did you get it?
So yeah, we're going to be looking at that structure
in a lot of depth. I know it's gone over two hours
on like two and a half hours today, but
it's what it is, isn't it? It's probably
good that you can do this.
If you can sit through and listen to me,
any adversity that comes from listening
to me for two hours is not even
half of the adversity you face as a trader.
Yeah, no, it's cool. It's cool.
I got nothing to do anyway, so.
but look you paid for it it's better than me pop you off
yeah exactly you could you could quite easily just say oh you know what
that's all you could have stopped it on an hour and said okay that's all
and then just left it I can wait your time
but obviously I'm up though hopefully that then makes sense
really the whole topic has been how the behaviour and the order
and the organisational rules of markets can affect prices
we finally reached the conclusion or this this notion
this concept that during these periods, it doesn't mean there's huge amounts of selling.
It's just the bi-liquidity that is supposed to be given to the market is not being given to it.
The bi-liquity disappears and it draws away, creating this thinness.
The effect is the sellers, imagine they will sell what liquidity here, yeah, sell limit orders.
Then some dickhead when market order sells short, buyers, you know, the bi-liquity disappeared.
the bid price
to put lower
making the volume
chase chase chase chase
the sell liquidity
remained there
selling dried off
hits on buy liquidity
like that's why
we went along here
and prices now
ran all the way back
to where there was a real
sell liquidity
yeah
right
it came back in like a vacuum
it came back
through the vacuum
drew back to the origin
what we call
the core area of liquidity
this is where the core
the bulk of the liquidity
is
now that alone
can help you to find areas
where you're likely to see
price responsiveness
where you're likely to see liquidity
and price respond of liquidity
you know
we have these middle areas
which are not so great
and these core areas
which are slightly better at the trader
get it
because the liquidity is there
this is where the real bids are going to be waiting
this is where the real offers are well waiting
and price went there
look I took a trade at this core
when you know earlier you said
said, oh, you made a live call, is because probability of the way this move happened,
it was quite thin down there, the way they ticked, all right?
The way the move was developing was showing weakness in sellers,
stretching out of the sellers combined with an area where you can expect consistently,
based off validation, based of experience, based off thousands and thousands of examples,
that price will respond there, that's it.
Yeah, you said it with your chest as well.
He was like, oh, it's going up.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the reason I can say
how much is I've validated. I don't need anybody else.
Like, I don't need anybody else to tell me that this
Jeterre. Like, I know is true. I've seen it happen time and time again.
So you need to do the same thing. You need to validate these things.
Even though what I'm saying, I challenge you to invalidate it.
You still have the onus to go unvalent.
You have the on yourself to go out and validate whatever's being discussed.
Never take anything that I'm discussing with you as, I was like,
as like gospel, if I've discussed a certain price behavior with you, try to unwell there,
try to find examples where it didn't work.
Do you get it?
And that way you inspect what you're learning.
That way you get to like, you're looking into the things that I'm telling you.
So we'll be like breaking down the structure, basically.
And we'll be given it specific categories and everything we're not looking to this now.
Before and we wanted that, we're going to have a PDF that we go through next session,
which is going to introduce you
to this idea of variable volume flow
which kind of explains how
why these price runs dry off
why the buying doesn't come in forever
and ever and ever
it kind of makes sense
yeah
also it gives you insight into this idea
that you know everybody calls
the FX market very liquid
it is liquid
it's liquid over time
so over a big enough time span
let's say 10 day period
yeah it's very liquid
but at any given second
like the volume shot here
the provision how much liquidity is provided
to the market can be almost
non-existent you get it
yeah yeah and people don't have
that capacity for nuance the small
shade in the detail to realize yeah it's
very liquid but not all the fucking time
and volume
isn't always common at the same
intensity you can have light volume
like right now you can have
heavy volume
in the morning yeah you said volume is a
constant. Yeah, exactly. So there are a lot of things like this provide, they're basically
principles. They give you insight into why we see what happens. We can expect volume to dry
off more often, more consistently than we can expect volume to continue coming in the same
direction forever and ever and ever in a market that is not dominated by speculators. If this was
a, if this was a market dominated by speculators, whenever someone's buying, I want to be a buyer as well.
Whenever someone's selling, I want to be a seller as well.
In this market, it's not.
We have liquidity on both sides of the market.
Volume is just, we'll discuss this stuff soon.
Next session.
One final thing.
Yeah, sorry.
This is the structure we're going to break down.
You have core areas.
You have the middle areas, which I call residual.
Yeah.
You're doing the left over a week.
and to give you an answer
I only trade at core areas
unless it's a high time frame move
unless it's like a H1 move like this
then yeah I'll trade in the middle
of the move as well like that
right
so hopefully there's more insight into
why we look into these things that we do
look at this trade at the high of the day today today
well how many poops was that off
four pips yeah
but that's my rule and I
I am not allowed to take trade
ahead of the level. Now, you might be thinking that price didn't respond off these. It didn't allow
a time frame. So if I pull up both of these levels, oh yeah, we're going to discuss as well
the characteristics of winners and losers, how you can take a trade, you can all look amazing and
well, and then subtly the probabilities change. And how we need to respond to that. So managing probabilities
as they shift.
So,
okay,
so we responded slightly,
it wasn't a great response,
but we respond off the second level,
I guess.
Also,
what we'll discuss is
how you can have
a million levels
that don't necessarily
mean they're going to be traded.
Yeah.
All right.
Level selection is 50%
the equation.
People place all their weight
on level selection.
It's only 50% the equation.
Why I won
is a combination of a good level
plus a weak move.
So price movement is also the over side of the equation.
It's never just level-based.
So it adds a bit of depth
and increase the probability of the initial trade.